If we talk about shares,
people who trade in shares are very
confused whether it will be considered as trading or
business or should it be
included in the slab of personal income.  What
is the matter with this?
See, what is the frequency, it depends
whether it is trading or investment.   If
you know it is trading then you buy and sell.
Like any goods are bought and sold.  It is
done like this.  So you will have to
show your shares stock in trade.
Like if a businessman does business, let's say
he has carts of some
food item or electricity, if he does any business then
if you declare your shares as stock and trade then it becomes
trading.  Now the
question is
where should the stock in trade be declared?
Stock and trade means when you maintain your account, the
stocks shown in that account, the
shares that you have in your hand will
go into the stock.
And as I told you the easy way to
understand.  Just like people buy and sell goods.
Those who are not traders will have any goods in the
Stock in Traded column.
Yes, stock in trade, stock and trade is a
character.   The
character is
that you have
declared the stock that you have holding.  They kept
taking from it, selling it and then putting it back into it.
This stock became in trade.  Meaning, they kept taking from it and
selling it.
This stock, so the
income generated from it will
come under the category of trading.
So that will go into trading and that will
go into income from business and profession.
Tax audit will be applicable on that
if your turnover is above Rs 10 crore, digital as it is
nowadays in shares, so that stock
and trade declaration and the biggest thing is that
you will be able to take the rebate of Rs 12 lakh under 87A because here under 80
you have now come under professional and business income.
Now, if you are not in capital gains then
that Rs 12 lakh for you, I am talking about the current year, it becomes Rs
12 lakh and
you can also claim some expenses in it.
In fact, this Lakshman is even here.  Perhaps very few
people know that if you have taken a
loan to do this business.   A
loan has been taken.
Okay,
and you are paying interest on that loan.
You can also deduct that interest from your profit.
However, I would like to mention this here.
You must be aware that
most of our viewers are connected to the stock market.
So I would like to tell you
that if you are doing derivatives trading then keep in
mind the observation of SEBI that 89% people lose money in derivatives.
Yes, you are doing swing trading
because some people also trade by taking delivery.
Now the question arises that
once you have declared trading apart from your investment.  Please pay
close
attention to this and a circular has also been issued on this by
a department.  Once you make the
announcement, you will have to remain
there consistently.  Trading cannot take place.
You did trading for one year, the other
said, no sir, I
want to trade it as capital gain for the second year.  I am
long term or short term capital, then in the
third year you started trading again.  This wo
n't work.  Once you have made a strategy,
this is a circular on that strategy.
You will have to stick to that strategy.
Why?  Why is it like this?  Because if you
change it again and again, it will cause
revenue loss to the department.  For your own benefit,
when you saw that you were getting more profit in capital gains at a lower
rate, you took it.  When
you saw that I was more into trading,
he took it.  So consistency is a word
in English.  You will have to maintain stability.  Be
careful whatever you are selecting.  Now Lakshman, there is one more very important
thing to add to this.
Now someone asked me, I want to take advantage of both.
I want to declare some shares in my stock and trade
and some shares now the
person was the same.
How can we take two characters each now?
also possible.  The solution to this is that you should have
two separate demat accounts.   That means
you are investing from one account
and trading from the other account.
And if you are taking capital gains, you would
know that you can also take the
rebate deduction of up to Rs 12,25,000 in equity under Section 112A.
In that you
can take up to Rs 12 lakh.
You can also avail the basic exemption limit of Rs 4 lakh for this year
in capital gains.  But
you will be able to get the one worth Rs 12 lakh only if you
declare it as trading.  So the basic mantra of
Lakshman is that those who are unable to decide whether to
go into capital gains or
trading, they should maintain consistency.
Choose it after thinking carefully and
then do not change it.
Okay, now explain one thing to me if I'm
confused.   Yes.
If we want to see from the tax point of view whether
we should be in trading or
investment.  So how to
see this thing?
Absolutely.  The answer lies in tax rates.
Now when you pay 12.5% ​​you will know that
I am taking long term capital gain as an example.  There
is tax and the
tax that is levied in trading is according to your slab.
Now what you should do is first
estimate
which slab I am in for the profit I am going to make
and how much tax I am going to have to pay in that slab.
Here, you can see in capital gains that
if I am getting long term capital gains, for
example, then see how much tax I have to pay at 12.5%.
One more thing to note is
that in this trading of yours,
Laxman, I saw that some people have opened a proper office
for trading.  There are
TV screens installed all over the place.  Staff is also
hired who provides the services and their
expenses are huge.  If you feel that your
trading expenses are too high then it may be
beneficial to go into trading.  So
you will know this by doing calculations.  If
you and I ever get a chance, we can sit together and
discuss this in detail, how you
can look at it in more detail.   Of
course, we have collars attached to us as well.
But before that I will ask you one more question,
suppose we have two accounts.
Yes,
suppose we have an account of some other trading account
of some other bank or demat account of some other company in
which we are just investing.
Another one is kept in which we are trading
or you have said many times that we can do this also.
So can we take advantage of both of these
?
Absolutely, the purpose of having two accounts is to
show capital gains in one.
But Lakshman, this also has to be seen that
trading in this means that you are buying quickly.
Selling quickly.
Investment means you keep the shares for some time, say a month or
two.  Yes, keeping it for one month, 2 months, 6
months, 1 year.  But the department does
n't force it on you through a circular.  The department only
tells you that once you select something,
you should stick to it.
You are saying that there should be a little more clarity in the circular
that a time should be
specified.
See Eliminating the Gray Area.
This Lakshman is very subjective.  Whenever the
government tried to force someone into trading
, he said I am an investor.  When trying to
pressure an investor, he said that I am a
trader.  So that's why the government left it.
Whatever you understand, whatever
you understand,
stick to whatever you do.   Stay tuned.
However, I say that
you should not leave that also.  A clear guideline was given that if you are
doing this then you will be considered trading.  If you are
doing this then
it is very difficult Lakshman because it
depends on the position of the stock market at that time.  Sometimes you have to
sell quickly.  I have seen even long-term
investors
buy and sell very quickly, and I have often
seen traders holding on to a single trade for three to four months.  So
this becomes very difficult.  Because it
depends on the changing conditions of the stock market.  That's why
they can't do it.  But Kohli
sir made it very clear that you
want to show trading, you
want to show investment.  There are many formulas from this.
It has various benefits from the tax point of view.